A Guide to the Papers of Mark Twain, 1862-1946
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Letters
  - [Jane Lampton Clemens] to Samuel E. [Moffett] with ANS on verso from Annie [Moffett] Webster, 1879 October 15; AL, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Re October 4 bank draft; mentions Orion Clemens, Charles L. (Webster), Pamela Clemens Moffett, and friends; wishes to be remembered to "Sam's Uncle Harvey." ANS at bottom from Annie (Moffett) Webster says she would write if she had time.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to William Winter with AN by [William Winter] at top, [1879] December 5; ACS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Praises Winter's poem "The Chieftain"; calls it a masterwork that seems perfect; would read it to his wife but he always breaks down when he reads the poem. S.L.C. AN at top by [William Winter] identifies poem as "The Chieftain."
  - John Munro, New Brunswick, Canada, to Mark Twain, 1879 December 20; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Hears he is "troubled with twins" and encloses something on how to raise them successfully; wishes him a good Christmas and New Year; says his writings are read with pleasure.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, 1880 April 23; ALS, 4 p. (Box 2)
    Thanks the Boyesens for their praises for his new book; surprised at the critical success and potential financial success of the book; because of Boyensen's praises, was encouraged to read publicly from new book at Joseph Twichell's "chapel" instead of using old material as he had planned; speaks of the strong impulse of writers to write, even for their wastebaskets. M.T.
  - Mark Twain to [Edwin Pond] Parker, [1880] May 15; ACS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Has been ill but is recovering fast; has paid off a debt; mentions poem in Parker's column today. M.T.
  - Mark Twain to Edward Howard House, [1880] October 6; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Invitation to come visit whenever it suits him. M.T.
  - Mark Twain to Edward Howard House, [1880] November 9; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Appreciates hearing Ulysses S. Grant not offended; spent weekend at [William Dean] Howells; family looking forward to House's visit. M.T.
  - Mark Twain to [Edwin Pond] Parker, [1880 December 22]; ALS, 4 p. (Box 2)
    Suggests he set "The Splendor Falls" to music; suggests possible instrumentation and vocals; hopes he'll "do it right." S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to (President-Elect) James Garfield, 1881 January 12; ALS, 4 p. (Box 2)
    Discusses his support for retention of Frederick Douglass for Marshall of Washington and warmly praises Douglass; mentions Charles J. Langdon. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to [Edward Howard] House, [1881] February 4; ANS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Urges him to submit articles to James R. Osgood; looking forward to seeing House and his daughter when they visit; had badly wanted to show him his own book but will not be able. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1881 February 19; ALS, 6 p. (Box 2)
    Regrets that they missed connections but hopes they will visit in May; will ask [William Dean] Howells about House's article; has recommended him to John Hay and General [Grover] Cleveland for a diplomatic post in Japan; reports what was said in discussion with Ulysses S. Grant on subject, who thinks House can fill post well but will appoint someone else instead; adds that he has not been able to convince Grant to write a book but Grant mentioned some stories which he does want to write down before his memories dim. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Francis Augustus Teall, 1881 April 22; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Says "sketch" accurate; suggests an addition listing his later books through A Tramp Abroad (1880); has a book ( The Prince and the Pauper ) in press but is not including it since it will be out in November. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to [James Ripley] Osgood, 1881 May 23; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Cover letter for check for $160.76; queries "London 6 vols" entry; prefers to keep his "Prince" account separate entirely; places book orders. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Branford, CT, to Charles [L. Webster], [1881] June 5; ALS, 3 p. (Box 2)
    Comments on various business matters; discusses royalties on his scrap book. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Branford, CT, to "Charley" [ Charles L. Webster], [1881 July 10]; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Discusses printing job; suggests finishing unspecified item in best style, and print in two colors; will be returning home by express. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to [James Ripley] Osgood, 1881 October 2; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Agrees to Osgood's interpretation of the Canadian publishing matter; inquires on how to make a transfer of unspecified item to Chatto & Windus. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, [1881] October 4; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Discusses remodelling of his home and admonishes House never to remodel. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1881 October 8; ALS, 3 p. (Box 2)
    Says he has not been in Boston since he and House "lunched" with [James Ripley] Osgood, [Thomas Bailey] Aldrich, and others; hopes to finish remodeling so that House and Koto, his daughter, may be able to visit; comment on progress of remodelling. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1881 October 21; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Glad for his opinion of the book ( The Prince and the Pauper ); discusses the problem of baronets in the book, possible ways including a foot-note to solve the problem, and the title to give Miles, one of the characters; hopes House can visit soon; visits Montreal in November with [William Dean] Howells and [James Ripley] Osgood. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1881 October 24; ALS, 3 p. (Box 2)
    Expresses gratitude for House's research into the baronet problem (in The Prince and the Pauper ) and resolving the foot-note proposal which neither Olivia or House liked; has sent his preferred correction to [James Ripley] Osgood, but will defer to Osgood's and House's judgement. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1881 October 26; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Glad that House's suggestion was adopted, but not sure if correction will be in time for London edition; [James Ripley] Osgood concerned change might affect copyright because of differing texts but he thinks not; decorators still at work but hopes soon to set date for House's visit.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1881 November 16; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Hopes more of remodelling completed by December 15 and that House and Koto can come then; is going to Canada in ten days hunting for copyrights but will be back by December 7. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1881 November 21; ALS, 3 p. (Box 2)
    Comments that he and Olivia greatly enjoyed House's recent Atlantic Monthly article; notes House was spared [Thomas Bailey] Aldrich's "butcher-knife" and marvels House was not sent proofs; going with [James Ripley] Osgood to Canada November 25; home almost ready for House's visit. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Sarah Pratt McLean [Greene], 1881 December 12; ALS, 3 p. (Box 2)
    Thoroughly enjoyed her book, as did his family and guests; has asked [James Ripley] Osgood to send her his new book. S.L.C.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain to Edward Howard House, 1881 December 27; ALS, 4 p. (Box 2)
    Arrangements for House's visit; suggests open-ended visit; visiting the Mississippi River with [James Ripley] Osgood in April; reports Olivia enjoyed Koto's Christmas cards; has had 6 of his books printed on China paper for Susy, "Bay," Koto and several other special friends. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Branford, CT, to James R. Osgood and Company, [1881 -1886] June 16; ANS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Introduces Charles Hopkinson Clark, one of the three who have agreed to compile the Library of Humour for Osgood and Company. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to James Ripley Osgood, 1882 January 4; ALS, 4 p. (Box 2)
    Has received india paper books; says McMillan (sic) matter is Osgood's and Dawson's to decide; does not care how many Canadian editions sold as long as they are not sold in the U.S.; discusses discounts to general agents, thinks discount wasted as the canvassers do all the work and will still current rate despite discount; concerns about books in the bookstores; encloses letter (not present) from a foreigner sent to him by Dean Sage; orders Joseph Henry Shorthouse's "John Inglesant"; mentions [Edward Howard] House and Koto visiting. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, 1882 January 11; ALS, 4 p. (Box 2)
    Delighted with his review of his book; mentions publishing book ( The Prince and the Pauper ) at own expense and his success as a publisher; thought Miss Gilder's letter was from a man and replied in kind; asks for his address and invites him to visit. (pages misnumbered in letter) S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Lucy [Hamilton] Hooper, Paris, 1882 January 21; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Recommends the young lady who bears this letter to Hooper as a translator of French on Orion Clemens's estimation; would be willing to visit Paris to dine with Hooper again but will not endure a foreign country again for any other purpose. S.L.C.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Charles Erskine Scott Wood with AN by Charles Erskine Scott Wood1882 February 21, TL, 1 p.
    Will visit with Joseph Twichell when their families are better; hopes to see "the charming Kentucky school girl" there; mentions that Generals Sherman and Van Vliet had copies of Date 1601 when he visited; says its circulation is slowly growing and a copy has gone to Japan; expects it will cause him trouble. S.L.C. Charles Erskine Scott Wood notes in AN at bottom that he was Adjutant to the Superintendent at U.S. Military Academy West Point at that time.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1882 February 23; TL, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Agrees with House's assessment of the Scribner's critical review of The Prince and the Pauper; surprised by the very complimentary English reviews; comments on great sales in England; pleased to have income from three books that can't be pirated; has rheumatism, but it allows him to practice typewriting (typed letter himself); family sick but getting better. Typed signature M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Charles Erskine Scott Wood with AN by Charles Erskine Scott Wood1882 April 3, TL, 1 p.
    Enclosing original manuscript of 1603 (sic) ( Date 1601 ); notes that there are many errors; suggests Wood correct them as necessary, as he is too busy to do so himself. S.L.C. Charles Erskine Scott Wood notes in AN that Twain forwarded manuscript of 1601 to him to be printed on the U.S. Military Academy West Point press, of which he was in charge; also comments on Twain's use of the typewriter.
  - Mark Twain to [James Ripley] Osgood, [1882 April 14]; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Plans for an April 17 trip with him; suggests hotel car to Chicago; can get sketches ready in time; says publishing books does not pay for the trouble writing them. M.T.
  - Mark Twain to Unknown; on verso Mark Twain to Charles Erskine Scott Wood with AN by Charles Erskine Scott Wood1882 August, ALS, 2 p.
    Writes to unknown correspondent he has quit the lecture platform permanently. On verso, ALS 1882 August Mark Twain to Charles Erskine Scott Wood says he and Twichell like "it (the one sent for his signature)." M.T. and S.L.C. Charles Erskine Scott Wood in AN says this statement probably refers to a proof of Timothy Cole's woodcut after Abbott Henderson Thayer's portrait of Twain.
  - Mark Twain, Elmira, NY, to [David L. Grasmere], 1882 September 14; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Unable to comply with his request; says he is not well and sends regrets. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to [James Ripley Osgood], 1882 October 18; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Sending [Charles L.] Webster to talk with him; would like Webster to have charge of running the book if possible. S.L.C.
  - Charles L. Webster, New York, to American Publishing Company, 1882 October 26; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Says Mark Twain has received check but check should have been sent to Webster; Twain wants business to be conducted through him; cannot send receipt since he did not receive the money.
  - Charles L. Webster to Frank E. Bliss, 1882 November 5; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Re business matters with American Publishing Company.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1882 December 2; TLS, 5 p. (Box 2)
    Has been struggling hard over his book for awhile, suffering "literary gout"; comments at length on the recent gubernatorial election in Connecticut lost by the Republicans, political journalism, and "bossism"; mentions family news and sleighing for the first time this winter. Typed signature S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT., to Horace Russell, 1882 December 12; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Re arrangements for his speech (at the New England Dinner 1882 December 23), "The Regular Toast, Woman --God Bless Her, Response by Mark Twain "; will speak fifth if President [Chester] Arthur not present; if he is, then sixth; felt other subjects too solemn; will be his last speech except for one in August which fulfills a three year old promise. S.L.C.] (w/env) (w/3 transcripts)
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Unknown, 1883 January 5; ANS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    "If you would be kindly spoken of, die. There is no other way. But don't hurry". S.L.C. and M.T.
  - Mark Twain to James R. Osgood and Company, 1883 January 6; ALS, 4 p. (Box 2)
    Requests two sets of plates and dies and 50,000 copies of book ( Life on the Mississippi ) printed; he will not cause delay but Olivia might because of her proofreading; wants them to look carefully at the Atlantic Monthly material; wants to provide Charles L. Webster with advertising so he won't complain later if book does not sell; places book orders. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Arthur Gilman, 1883 January 8; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Unable to aid him in request since he is occupied with putting a book to press; suggests he contact Rev. Francis Goodwin for help. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to George E. Waring [Jr.], 1883 April 6; AL, 3 p. (Box 2)
    Fragment. Apologizes for inviting Col. Waring when there is no room for him; suggests alternate arrangements; says George Washington Cable did well in speech with Parson Jones story. No signature.
  - Mark Twain, Elmira, NY, to Kingsland Smith, St. Paul, MN, 1883 July 28; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Asks where July dividend is because he has not seen it; will not be in Hartford this summer. S.L.C.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1883 October 1; ALS, 5 p. (Box 2)
    Discusses [Joseph] Twichell's well-meant premature publication of Twain's letter on his invented "historical game" in the [Hartford] Courant; says this upset his own plans for a small book; mentions having House's proofs and playing word games; [William Dean] Howells and [James Ripley] Osgood back from Europe; remarks "we" have been home two weeks. M.T.] (includes brief crossed-out notes on verso of p. 4 and 5 by House)
  - Frank E. Bliss to Charles L. Webster, 1883 November 7; ALS (copy), 1 p. (Box 2)
    Requests names of publishers who could manufacture A Tramp Abroad for less than he can.
  - Charles L. Webster to [American Publishing Company], 1883 November 14; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Thinks S. W. Green's Sons will do the work below American Publishing Company prices.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1883 November 12; TL, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Jokes about family's reaction to gift House sent them from Japan. Typed signature S.L.C.
  - Frank E. Bliss to S. W. Green's Sons, 1883 November 17; ALS (copy), 1 p. (Box 2)
    Asks whether they wish to submit a bid on printing two thousand copies of A Tramp Abroad; gives specifications; suggests J. P. Jones can lend them a copy if they show him this letter.
  - S. W. Green to American Publishing Company, 1883 November 20; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Charles M. Green Printing Company can supply two thousand copies of A Tramp Abroad for 53 cents a book as soon as the paper can be made, if American Publishing Company supplies the frontispiece portrait.
  - Frank E. Bliss to Unknown, 1883 November; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Contends that, despite Mark Twain and Charles L. Webster's claims to the contrary, other publishers would have cost more to manufacture A Tramp Abroad.
  - Frank E. Bliss to Charles L. Webster, 1883 December 11; ALS (copy), 1 p. (Box 2)
    Has gotten price for manufacturing A Tramp Abroad from S. W. Green but says it would cost more; is making new edition "here" as before.
  - Orion Clemens, Keokuk, IA, to Samuel E. Moffett and Pamela Clemens Moffett, Kingsburgh, CA, 1884 January 13; ALS, 6 p. (Box 2)
    Discusses family financial affairs, health, friendly gossip about neighbors and old friends, and weather; glad to hear he has a farm.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1884 January 14; ALS, 4 p. (Box 2)
    Discusses House's precarious health; lists what he has been reading and comments on his reading habits; mentions Charley Delmonico; has been reminiscing with Thomas Bailey Aldrich about House, Artemus (Ward), and the rest of the "Pfaff gang"; writing new book which is moving along well. M.T.
  - William L. Hughes, Paris, to [Mark Twain ], 1884 February 14; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    His publisher Mr. Hennuyer requests Twain's approval of his translation of Adventures of Tom Sawyer about to be published and is now being illustrated by Achille Siriony; would also like approval of his forthcoming Adventures of Huckleberry Finn translation; Adventures of Tom Sawyer will be in same style as his adaptation of Helen's Babies of which he sends Twain a copy.
  - Mark Twain to Augustin Daly, 1884 February 17; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Requests Daly to look over his dramatization of Adventures of Tom Sawyer. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1884 February 27; ALS, 3 p. (Box 2)
    Discusses authorship of The Bread Winner and possibility of either John Hay or Clarence King as author; mentions George Washington Cable, while visiting, had the mumps for three weeks and comments on Cable's complaining; appreciates photographs of Koto; [William Dean] Howells just arriving. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Andrew Chatto, 1884 March 3; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Has referred "another one of those fellows" ( William L. Hughes ) to London publisher Chatto; keeping back Adventures of Huckleberry Finn until spring for a longer canvass. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, to "Dear Sir" [ Lorenz Rohr], editor of a Leavenworth, Kansas, German-language newspaper, [18]84 May 12; ALS, 1 p. w/env (Box 2)
    In response to a request from Rohr regarding Rohr's translation of Heine's "Lorelei." A photostatic copy of Rohr's letter and envelope to Twain is included.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1884 May 23; ALS, 5 p. (Box 2)
    Has forgotten about The Bread Winner; trying with Joseph Twichell to learn to bicycle; enjoyed the "catagraphs" but mourns that after years of longing is still catless. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Elmira, NY, to [American Publishing Company], 1884 August 11; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Presses company to bring suit at once against "these pirates" and threatens to annul his contracts with them on grounds that sufficient effort was not made to protect his copyrights. S.L.C.] (glued to card)
  - Mark Twain, Elmira, NY, to [George] Iles, 1884 September 8; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Thanks him; after lecture dates are set, will write him; hopes the dates are as Iles suggests. S.L.C.
  - Charles [L. Webster], San Francisco, CA, to Pamela Clemens Moffett and Samuel E. Moffett, 1884 October 28; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Thanks for their letters of introduction and directions; plans to finish his business and then will stay with them on the way back; promises family news.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1884 October 31; ALS, 3 p. (Box 2)
    Has forgotten favor House requested; wished he could visit Japan but thinks his daughters' musical education would suffer; possibly could go if he could find a competent house keeper to help Olivia; setting off on lecture tour; plans to vote Democratic and against [James G.] Blaine in the upcoming elections. M.T.
  - Mark Twain to [Chatto & Windus ], 1884 November 5; ALS, 3 p. (Box 2)
    Acknowledges receipt of their September 12 payment; thinks [James G.] Blaine may been defeated; Charles L. Webster in California is establishing book agencies; lecturing tonight first time in 8 or 10 years but will be last time ever; hopes to repeat their success in Canada. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Indianapolis, IN, to Estes and Lauriat, 1885 January 7; ALS, 3 p. (Box 2)
    Discusses a suit against Estes and Lauriat of Boston for their illegal sale of one of his books; says the matter is in hands of his lawyers, Alexander and Green of New York. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Henrietta C. Cosgrave, Chicago, IL, with TN 1930 March 12 from Helen M. Wilcox, 1885 April 11; ALS, 3 p. (Box 2)
    Marked "Private." Corrects the information given in newspaper article; says at 15 he promised his mother not to drink and was later released from pledge; kept his promise because he made it to his mother; expresses opinion on pledges given to temperance workers; has marked letter private since he did not want to contradict his mother's recollections in public and because of his opinion about temperance pledges. S.L.C. With TN 1930 March 12 (w/env) from Helen M. Wilcox, Mrs. Cosgrave's daughter, about the circumstances of her mother's correspondence.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to George Iles, 1885 April 27; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Had already read and profited by "it"; comments hotel in the right management now. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1885 May 13; AL, 5 p. (Box 2)
    Grieved to hear of House's illness but glad he is recovering; comments on Ulysses S. Grant and his memoirs; wishes Grant had written memoirs earlier; judges book as one of the best narratives in English language; Grant is finishing volume two but may have written his last; compares what his company offered Grant to The Century in royalties and subscription apparatus; discusses Grant's Century articles and why he should have been paid more; Olivia is pleased by Koto's gift. M.T. ("SLC per JR")
  - Mark Twain, Elmira, NY, to Edward Howard House, 1885 July 21; ALS, 6 p. (Box 2)
    Discusses publication of Ulysses S. Grant's memoirs; refutes published stories, which he thinks were spread by The Century; explains how his contract will generate more money for Grant that The Century offers; mentions anticipated sales; denies he got the book through underhanded means; adds that none of Grant's sons is a partner; looking forward to House's visit. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Frank Fuller, 1885 September 28; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Wished to talk to Fuller about a potential investment. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Unknown, 1885 December 26; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Re a watch Olivia L. Clemens bought some days ago which needs to be fixed. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Unknown, 1886 February 2; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Has had his say in the current The Century and to the Committee; does not enjoy writing miscellaneous articles. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1886 May 26; ALS, 6 p. (Box 2)
    Recounts anecdotally Olivia's disappointment that Koto could not visit. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, [1886] June 5; ALS, 3 p. (Box 2)
    Says that Koto's visit was a great success and all miss her including the family, Charles Dudley Warner, Miss Duke, Mamie Perkins, the Goldthwaites, and Miss Covey. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Elmira, NY, to Edward Howard House, [1886] June 16; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)